<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Website of Fergus Fettes</title>
    <link>https://www.fergusfettes.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Website of Fergus Fettes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 16:01:39 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.fergusfettes.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Music-I-Like</title>
      <link>https://www.fergusfettes.com/posts/music-i-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 16:01:39 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.fergusfettes.com/posts/music-i-like/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like listening to music. I try to listen widely, but also (somewhat) deeply, getting into niche genres and exploring the landscapes I find there. I had a quite tepid entry into music appreciation, growing up listening to Leonard Cohen, Bob Dylan, the Red Hot Chili Peppers, and whatever happened to be popular at the time among my peers (I&amp;rsquo;m of the Limp Bizkit generation so you can image what that means).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was at university, in my early 20s, my musical horizons were broadened, and continued to broaden throughout my twenties. I started listening more and more widely not only to &amp;lsquo;popular&amp;rsquo;, contemporary music, but also taking a fairly slow, broad pass through the history of classical music. Below I have summarized some of my listening habits of the past ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;spotify&#34;&gt;Spotify&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using spotify for almost ten years now. Back in the day I used to like songs and make playlists, but for the past 7 years or so I have listened almost exclusively to albums. I curate my downloaded albums quite closely, deleting things that become too familiar (though there are many guilty pleasures that I download and delete again and again) and always making sure I have a good collection of unfamiliar music downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To deal with the fact that I always deleted music I know, I realised I needed a hardcopy of my listening habits. So I got a little book in which I would periodically write down the best music I had been listening to recently. Sometimes I would forget to update it for quite a while, but generally every month or two I would write down some highlights. In the front of the book I wrote down &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; music, in the back &amp;lsquo;popular&amp;rsquo; albums. I recently digitized these lists&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on my journey home (a disasterous train journey from London during a Tier 4 lockdown). Looking at them, I feel like they are strangely sparse and sad. I love listening to music and do it almost incessantly. Are these two lists really representative of what feels like such a significant part of my life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to delve further, I also &lt;a href=&#34;https://watsonbox.github.io/exportify/&#34;&gt;exported&lt;/a&gt; my old Liked/Starred Songs playlist&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Cringeworthy as some of my old taste is, I feel like this works better as an active snapshot of listening, and I recently started starring songs again. My intention with my starred list is not to create a playlist that I would particularly want to listen to, but to keep a record of songs from albums I like. So every song on my new list should been seen as a pointer to an album (though they are of course normally my favourite or the most catchy song). I will export and update this list regularly&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and probably rotate every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Spotify is only a small part of my listening. Here I will list some other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;youtube&#34;&gt;Youtube&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youtube is a fantastic source for curated piano music. This is my main reason to go there. Here are some of the best channels I&amp;rsquo;m aware of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/c/AshishXiangyiKumar/&#34;&gt;Ashish Xiangyi Kumar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The classic &amp;lsquo;wonderfully curated piano music with blurbs and sheets&amp;rsquo;. Long may Xiangyi rule the channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC5g-oLzgpp4Ygzj5J6SU04Q&#34;&gt;Medtnaculus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another good one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCiiU81VkgBw6oK9tKwlKNgA&#34;&gt;Flavi Chan Samurai Music Investigator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freaky music from all over the world with a strong oriental inclination. Some of my favourite discoveries are either from here or present here (Miharu Koshi, Haruomi Hosono, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iR95HxKfWcE&#34;&gt;this track&lt;/a&gt; which has to be one of my favourite grooves of all time).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youtube is also a great for really weird stuff that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t show up in most musical catalogues, like a 20-minute long piano interpretation of Kavinskys Outrun which I once saw and (to my enduring regret) didn&amp;rsquo;t immediately download, or fantastic pieces like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wJWksPWDKOc&#34;&gt;everywhere at the end of time&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VXxZCSAWUP8&#34;&gt;this 5-and-a-half hour long piece&lt;/a&gt; trying to get you used to a different tuning method. Or shaky-cam home footage of unusual choirs from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I have a weakness for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VN562bgJRZ4&#34;&gt;Anthony &amp;lsquo;Best Teeth in the Game&amp;rsquo; Fantano&lt;/a&gt; and have gotten several recommendations from him. I can&amp;rsquo;t claim that this is the most profound source in the world but he does fine work nevertheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also watch Adam Neely sometimes, but not for his reccis. Minor shoutout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;vk-russian-facebook&#34;&gt;VK (Russian Facebook)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to their very relaxed copyright policies, VK is a great place to find wonderfully well curated collections on particular niche topics, particularly stuff that you might struggle to find elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I was using it to explore Japanese pop music from the 70s and 80s (City Pop, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jZpeH_UfNiQ&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for an example). &lt;a href=&#34;https://vk.com/the_yamashitter&#34;&gt;Yamashitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://vk.com/stoiclady&#34;&gt;properly tagged jpop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://vk.com/vintagejpop&#34;&gt;vintage jpop&lt;/a&gt; are a good place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However their &amp;lsquo;Awesome Tapes From Africa&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://vk.com/tapesfromafrica&#34;&gt;section&lt;/a&gt; is also great. (I mean you could also just follow that record label of course.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;other&#34;&gt;Other&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;soulseek&#34;&gt;Soulseek&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t gotten much into it yet but I hear it is the dream for things that can&amp;rsquo;t be found elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;soundcloud&#34;&gt;Soundcloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only use Soundcloud to listen to &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/youcancallmeoliver/yutxtmeruhiwuu2doucry&#34;&gt;this one song&lt;/a&gt; that was produced by a friend of a friend, and my old partners &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/urssauvage&#34;&gt;solo stuff&lt;/a&gt;. I should really dive in there for the really cutting edge stuff, I know. But I tend to listen to much more older and more established music than the state-of-the-art. That is neither to my credit nor discredit in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I want to here some opinions about the music I like. I generally look up whatever album I&amp;rsquo;m considering on Pitchfork on these occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, there are two sources I should mention: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scaruffi.com/music.html&#34;&gt;Piero Scaruffi&lt;/a&gt;, a physicist I think? I have no idea how I discovered that list, but I have gotten some good stuff from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tedgioia.com/bestalbumsof2019.html&#34;&gt;Ted Gioia&lt;/a&gt;. I am working through that list just now. Having gotten halfway through 2019, I&amp;rsquo;m realising that I need to start skipping the jazz and the folk singers that he recommends, but there is so much weird and fascinating stuff from all over on those lists that I think he will continue to be a great source for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conculsions-and-acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Conculsions and Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank the youtube algorithm and the many many youtube channels that I cannot credit because I have never known them, for their tireless work. I think it is very likely that the sources credited above (which the exception of &amp;lsquo;spotify, generally&amp;rsquo;) actually make up a small proportion of what I listen to, with much more coming from diverse sources in the youtube or spotify algorithmic radio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank ublock origin for making youtube bearable. (I pay for Spotify, but do not do so with the mistaken believe that that constitutes supporting artists.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to acknowledge that in fact, most of my musical journey (at least in contemporary music) has been driven largely by the fact that I have had the very good fortune to live with people who have been various degrees of music journalist/musician/music obsessive, and it was these people who set me on my way and kept me on the straight and narrow; in approximate order of when they started supplying me regularly with reccis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kevin Mulligan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hanna Lemmik&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diarmuid Morgan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emma Ludwig&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Felix Opper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sophie Nam Koong&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And special mentions to Felix Mulligan, my brother Max, and Gesa Maass for contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fergusfettes.com/lists/classical-2013-2020/&#34;&gt;www.fergusfettes.com/lists/classical-2013-2020/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fergusfettes.com/lists/popular-2013-2020/&#34;&gt;www.fergusfettes.com/lists/popular-2013-2020/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fergusfettes.com/lists/spotify-2011-2013/&#34;&gt;www.fergusfettes.com/lists/spotify-2011-2013/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fergusfettes.com/lists/spotify-2020-2021/&#34;&gt;www.fergusfettes.com/lists/spotify-2020-2021/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alacritty Ascii</title>
      <link>https://www.fergusfettes.com/posts/alacritty-ascii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 21:56:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.fergusfettes.com/posts/alacritty-ascii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alacritty/alacritty&#34;&gt;Alacritty&lt;/a&gt; is one of the many lovely developer tools that are springing up as the first flush in the Rust revolution. Its a fantastic terminal that I&amp;rsquo;m sure I will have more to say about in due time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/micros/alacritty-and-ascii/&#34;&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt;, I discovered something lovely while transferring some files the other day. I was moving my small film collection (currently stretching to 7 titles: &amp;lt;INSERT FILMS&amp;gt;) from one computer to another, and I just wanted to sanity check that the transfer had succeeded. So I sshed into the machine &lt;code&gt;ssh work&lt;/code&gt; and ran &lt;code&gt;vlc -I dummy ~/films/Mullholland\ Dr.mkv&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine my surprise to see the criterion logo appear, animated before me. Here is a nice still from another film to illustrate:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/alacritty-ascii/still_face.png&#34; alt=&#34;face closeup&#34; title=&#34;Closeup of face&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also look at a copy-paste of the terminal &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/alacritty-ascii/still_face.txt&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to prove that it really is ASCII output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zooming out, the resolution becomes better and better (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/alacritty-ascii/still_face_large.txt&#34;&gt;text&lt;/a&gt;), but it starts to jitter quite badly at a certain size.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/alacritty-ascii/still_face_large.png&#34; alt=&#34;large face&#34; title=&#34;Closeup of face&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the ssh connection might be a bottleneck, so I went to the computer to try it on one machine. I had that slightly haunted feeling that the magic might disappear, and when I entered the terminal I suddenly wondered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will I get it to work here? If I run &lt;code&gt;vlc -I dummy ~/filmes/Crash.mkv&lt;/code&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll just get a window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but as soon as the thought was there I realised I could just start with &lt;code&gt;ssh localhost&lt;/code&gt;. And it worked. I was watching the &amp;lsquo;Universal&amp;rsquo; logo barge into my terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But things got even better. I noticed that my keystrokes were even getting sent back to vlc, so I could skip forward, pause and even quit the film (sometimes it gets stuck and I have to &lt;code&gt;killall vlc&lt;/code&gt; but so it goes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a little sleuthing, I notice that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;vlc -I dummy ~/films/film.choice
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;is interactive, but&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;vlc ~/films/film.choice
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;is not. What is this dummy terminal doing after all? Well, the vlc wiki has a little info&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and they nicely point out that keystrokes are sent back. I find the terminology a little odd, since &amp;lsquo;dummy video output&amp;rsquo; is just normal video output, but I think they are looking at it from a gui-makers perspective. And this seems to be the key&amp;ndash; with the dummy interface, vlc streams the movie to a window. Alacritty is presumably pretending to be a screen or a window of some sort, in order to pass its work to the GPU, so VLC merrily dumps the video stream in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I would love to know, and I might take some time to investigate, is how is Alacritty mapping the video stream to ASCII? And why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will leave this story here for now. I have two things in mind: one, to investigate further over at the Alacritty github and two, to have some people round for a film, run it through Alacritty-ASCII and run the audio through a digital soundcard or some synths, and make a little performance. I&amp;rsquo;ll update if either of these things transpire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, if you want to try it yourself, I have uploaded a slightly rushed video of the effect in action (the size limit on asciinema was not made with 4k ASCII movies in mind, so no hard feelings). Asciinema cast attached&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is a final zoomed in still to admire. In the attached &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/alacritty-ascii/muscle_kid_small.txt&#34;&gt;text&lt;/a&gt; you can see how much of a difference the color makes, presumably a lot of the 8s have the same foreground and background color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.fergusfettes.com/alacritty-ascii/muscle_kid_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;muscle kid&#34; title=&#34;Kid with muscles&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.videolan.org/Documentation:Modules/dummy/&#34;&gt;https://wiki.videolan.org/Documentation:Modules/dummy/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://asciinema.org/a/378193&#34;&gt;https://asciinema.org/a/378193&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

